Guide to the Edith Kramer Papers MC.215
New York University Archives
- Series V: Artwork, 1937-2000
  - Sub-Series B: Artwork Created During Art Therapy, 1951-2000
    After leaving Wiltwyck, Kramer worked as an art therapist at the Leak and Watts Children's Home, the Turtle Bay Music School, the Guild School of the Jewish Guild for the Blind, and the Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Department of Child.
    - [angel and devil], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      This artwork was created at Wiltyck School for Boys between 1951 and 1957.
      18 x 22 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Do not remove hinges until 2099; they conceal private health information.
    - [birds], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      24 1/2 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [children, sun, and moon], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      24 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on red paper, varnished.
      Do not remove hinges until 2099; they concealing private health information.
    - [creature with antennae], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      12 9/16 x 14 7/16 inches. transparent and opaque paints on paper, varnished.
    - [creature], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 23 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books.
    - [figure with large bottle], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      This artwork created at Wiltyck School for Boys between 1951 and 1957.
      18 x 24 inches, matte opqaue paint on paper, varnished
    - [gallows], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      24 x 18 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [guillotine], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      this artwork was created at Wiltyck School for Boys between 1951 and 1957.
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith, 1958. Art Therapy in a Children's Community. Springield, Ill.: Thomas; and Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books.
    - [injured head], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished.
    - [injured whale], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Do not alter the position of window mat before 2099; it concealsing private health information.
    - [king with large crown], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      19 3/8 x 25 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Do not remove patch on recto until 2099; it concealsing private health information.
    - [ocean scene], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [painting of sun with red mouth and blue eyes], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
    - [portrait of figure in Native American headdress], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      12 x 9 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [portrait of two faces], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, two 8.5 x 11 inches papers moutned with staples (one reproduction one graphite)
      Do not alter the position of window mat until 2099; it concealsing private health information.
    - [portrait with black eye], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint and charcoal on paper, varnished
      Do not change window mat location or remove hinges until 2099; they concealing private health information.
    - [ships at sea], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      32 x 40 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
      Do not remove hinges or patch on recto until 2099; they are conceal private health information.
    - [smoking man], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      17 1/4 x 13 1/2 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [snowflake with two red suns], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      9 x 14 inches, matte opque paint on paper, varnished
      Do not remove hinges until 2099; they are conceal private health information.
    - [sun with teeth], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      19 3/4 x 25 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books; and Kramer, Edith. 2000a. Art as Therapy: Collected Papers. London; Philadelphia: Jessica Kingsley Publishers.
    - [whale dying], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      14 x 20 inches, matte opque paint on paper
      Do not remove hinges or window mat until 2099; they concealing personal health information.
    - Brooding Witch Doctor, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - Dancing Beauty and Dancing Colt or Family of Horses, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books.
    - Devil, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      23 3/4 x 18 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - Egyptian Princess, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      24 x 35 1/2inches, matte opaque paint on brown paper, varnished
      Do not remove hinges or patch on recto until 2099; they conceal private health information.
    - Grinning Witch Doctor, 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 1/4 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - Hawk Chasing Rabbitt -11 Year Old or Rabbit Pursued by Vulture, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, charcoal on paper, varnished
    - Horse Against Rider, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      24 1/4 x 18 1/4 inches, matte opque paint on paper, varnished
    - Indian Chief, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      36 1/8 x 24 1/4 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - King, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
    - Mare and Colt, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      10 1/2 x 11 3/4 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished.
    - Mare and Colt, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
    - Moby Dick, The White Whale, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 48 inches, matte opaque paint on illustration board, varnished
    - Monster, Matthew, 13 years old, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      30 x 27 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, mounted to Mastonite, varnished
    - On Way Home from Train, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      6 1/8 x 8 3/4 inches, graphite on paper, varnished
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books; and Art Therapy in a Children's community
    - Playful Horses, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
    - Playground Sketches, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      Two (2) 10 x 7 1/2 inches, graphite on paper, varnished
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith, 1958. Art Therapy in a Children's Community. Springield, Ill.: Thomas.
      Do not reposition the window mat until 2099; it concealsing private health information.
    - Radiant Sun, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      17 1/2 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - Spanish Dancer, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      24 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - The Art Teacher, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      13 1/4 x 11 inches, graphite on paper, varnished
      Do not remove patch on recto until 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - The Art Teacher, 10 1/2 year, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 12 inches, charcoal on paper, varnished
      Do not remove patch on recto or hinges until 2099; they concealing private health information.
    - The Eskimo, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      19 x 22 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - The Mother, 11 years old, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
    - Wedding, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      24 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on violet paper, varnished
    - [diptych of candles], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 12 inches each, matte opaque paint on black paper, varnished.
    - [child with pink petals], ca. 1951-2000 (Box 99)
      Artwork likely created by Edith Kramer as a demostration work
    - [owl with hare], ca. 1951-2000 (Box 99)
      Artwork was likely created by Edith Kramer as a demostration work.
      24 x 18 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [pond in forest with two figures], ca. 1951-2000 (Box 99)
      18 1/4 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper.
    - Prisoner by William "Butch" Bosket, ca. 1953-1957 (Box 99)
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books; and with artist's identify reveal in Butterfield, Fox. 1995. All God's Children: The Bosket Family and the American Tradition of Violence. New York: Knopf: Distributed by Random House.
    - Young Man with Switchblade by William "Butch" Bosket, 1957 (Box 99)
      36 x 47 1/2 inches, matte opaque paint on paper mounted to Masonite, varnished.
    - [drawing of a woman], ca. 1958-1971 (Box 99)
      This artwork was created by art therapy receipent "Angel" as part of an autobiography.
      18 x 24 inches, charcoal on paper varnished
      Do not reposition window mat until 2099; it concealsing private health information.
    - [portrait of a boy with a speech bubble], ca. 1958-1971 (Box 99)
      14 1/8 x 22 inches
    - My art teacher, Edith Kramer, ca. 1958-1971 (Box 99)
      12 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches
      Do not reposition of window mat until 2099; it concealsing private health information.
    - [figure with oversized muscles], 1958-1972 (Box 99)
    - [figure with torch and baby in basket], ca. 1958-1971 (Box 99)
      12 x 18 inches, charcoal on paper, varnished
    - Hercunles, ca. 1958-1979 (Box 99)
      This artwork is titled "Hercunles" but it appears to be a depiction of Hercules.
      12 x 18 inches, charcoal on paper
      Do not remove tape; it conceals private health information and was applied by Edith Kramer.
    - [portrait of Edith Kramer], ca. 1958-1979 (Box 99)
      This artwork created by art therapy receipent "Angel" as part of an autobiography.
      19 x 13 inches, black matte opaque paint on paper, varnished.
      Do not reposition the window mat until 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - [color squiggles], ca. 1958-1979 (Box 99)
      16 3/4 x 29 1/2 inches
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith. 1979. Childhood and Art Therapy: Notes on Theory and Application, edited by Laurie Wilson. New York: Schocken Books.
    - [painting of a house], ca. 1958-1979 (Box 99)
      26 1/2 x 21 7/8 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith (1979) Childhood and Art Therapy: Notes on Theory and Application by Edith Kramer, Schoken.
      Do not remove hinges until 2099; they concealsing private health information.
    - Sunset Over The Bronx, ca. 1958-1979 (Box 99)
      18 x 24 inches, opaque paint on colored paper, varnished
    - [bombing of an airfield], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 99)
      13 3/4 x 17 inches, crayon on paper
    - [cartoon characters], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 99)
    - [colorful diagonal lines], 1958-2000 (Box 99)
      19 3/4 x 26 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [crowd], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 99)
      18 7/8 x 25 inches, black porous pointed pen on paper
    - [outdoor concert], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 99)
    - [two figures one with horns], 1958-2000 (Box 99)
      Black matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [underwater scene, figure with shark], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 99)
      9 x 12 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [untitled cityscape with sun drawing], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 99)
      18 x 12 inches, crayon on paper
    - [colorful lines], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 99)
      24 x 18 inches, crayon on paper
    - [portrait with braids and headdress], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 99)
      18 x 12 inches, graphite with matte opaque paint on paper